Jingeon.
Jingeon.
I told you to stay out of this!
Aku sudah bilang jangan ikut campur!
You're...
Kau...
Yes. Do you get it now?
Ya. Apa kau mengerti sekarang?
Do you remember who you killed?
Ingat siapa yang kau bunuh?
Do you now realize what your sin is?
Kini kau sadar apa dosamu?
What does that mean?
Apa artinya itu?
There's one more thing that annoys me.
Ada satu hal lagi yang mengusikku.
It's the thought of you hanging out with him,
Memikirkan kau bergaul dengannya meski tahu siapa dia sebenarnya.
Explain?
Jelaskan?
Did you know about him?
Apa kau tahu tentangnya?
-Know what? -This guy's identity.
- Tahu apa? - Identitas pria ini.
No way.
Tak mungkin.
I thought I was mistaken.
Kukira aku salah.
What do you mean by that?
Apa maksudmu?
Whom did he kill?
Siapa yang dia bunuh?
Is it Momyeong?
Apakah Momyeong?
Did he kill Momyeong?
Dia membunuh Momyeong?
It's childish, but I thought I should give him a chance.
Aku tahu ini kekanakan, tapi kuberi dia kesempatan.
Although nothing would've changed even with a proper answer.
Walau tak ada yang akan berubah bahkan dengan jawaban yang tepat.
You said you only tell the truth.
Katamu kau hanya berkata jujur.
I don't lie.
Aku tak berbohong.
I'm not immature.
Aku tidak kekanakan.
I only speak the truth.
Aku mengatakan kebenaran.
For the past 1,200 years,
Selama 1.200 tahun terakhir,
I've killed you in my head countless times.
aku membunuhmu di kepalaku berkali-kali.
You probably have no idea how much I wanted our powers to be swapped.
Kau mungkin tak tahu betapa aku ingin kekuatan kita bertukar.
of life and death in that cave for thousands of years.
di gua itu selama ribuan tahun.
The thought of you rotting like that...
Membayangkan kau membusuk seperti itu,
made me realize that it's probably the sweetest revenge.
itu mungkin balas dendam terhebat.
But...
Tapi...
you get to see the sun and breathe like this?
melihat matahari dan bernapas seperti ini?
How dare you breathe and smile?
Beraninya kau bernapas dan tersenyum?
Stop it.
Hentikan.
That's enough.
Cukup.
He's not picking up.
Dia tak menjawab.
When did he meet him for the first time?
Kapan dia bertemu dengannya pertama kali?
And what? For the past 1,200 years?
Lalu 1.200 tahun terakhir ini?
Also, the cave. What does that mean?
Juga, gua itu. Apa maksudnya?
Do you think Jingeon will be okay?
Apa Jingeon tak apa-apa?
I think he stopped his power in the middle of it.
Kurasa dia menghentikannya di tengah-tengah.
Had he used it fully, it would've been very bad.
Jika dia pakai sepenuhnya, sangat buruk.
And who's Momyeong?
Dan siapa Momyeong?
You don't know him?
Kau tak kenal dia?
His twin brother.
Saudara kembarnya. Dia seperti bayangan Biryeom.
Biryeom was so fond of him.
Biryeom sangat menyayanginya.
At some point, I realized that he was nowhere to be seen.
Suatu hari, aku sadar dia tak ada.
I had no idea that was what happened.
Aku tak tahu itu yang terjadi.
I should've paid more attention.
Harusnya lebih kuperhatikan.
Don't feel guilty.
Jangan merasa bersalah.
You've always been indifferent toward Biryeom.
Kau selalu tak acuh pada Biryeom.
Why didn't he tell me, though?
Kenapa dia tak memberitahuku?
Can't you see that I can't tell you because it's you?
Apa kau tak paham ini karena kau?
Because you're the one asking me for an explanation...
Karena kau yang meminta penjelasan...
Why...
Kenapa...
Why did he...
Kenapa dia...
-kill Momyeong? -I don't know.
- membunuh Momyeong? - Aku tak tahu.
I'm very disappointed in Mr. Shin.
Aku sangat kecewa pada Pak Shin.
You gods think of yourselves as saviors.
Kalian para dewa berpikir kalian penyelamat.
But what can you do to me?
Tapi bisa apa kau padaku?
Do you plan to kill me or what?
Kau berencana membunuhku?
Can you do...
Apa kau bisa...
a better job in doing that than I can?
lebih baik dalam pekerjaanku?
For the past 1,200 years,
Selama 1.200 tahun ini, aku membunuhmu di kepalaku berkali-kali.
You had to live through the endless vicious cycle of
Kau hidup dalam siklus hidup dan mati
life and death in that cave for thousands of years.
di gua itu selama ribuan tahun.
The thought of you rotting like that
Membayangkan kau membusuk seperti itu,
made me realize that it's probably the sweetest revenge.
itu mungkin balas dendam terhebat.
But...
Tapi kau...
you get to see the sun and breathe like this?
melihat matahari dan bernapas seperti ini?
How dare you breathe and smile?
Beraninya kau bernapas dan tersenyum?
MR. SHIN HU-YE
PAK SHIN HU-YE
Don't worry.
Jangan cemas.
Biryeom pulled a prank.
Biryeom membuat lelucon.
-He'll sort it out with his-- -He's like you guys, isn't he?
- Dia... - Dia seperti kalian, 'kan?
I'm talking about Mr. Shin.
Maksudku Pak Shin.
He's from your world, isn't he?
Dia dari duniamu?
-Why didn't you tell me? -Did I have to tell you?
- Kenapa kau tak bilang? - Haruskah?
-Sorry? -You never asked.
- Apa? - Kau tak bertanya.
He's not like us.
Dia tak seperti kami.
But...
Tapi itu...
It must've been you guys.
pasti kalian.
-What? -I'm sure of it.
- Apa? - Aku yakin.
Those who told Mr. Shin that he shouldn't have been born.
Yang berkata Pak Shin seharusnya tak dilahirkan.
Since when...
Sejak kapan...
were you two close enough to talk about such things?
kalian dekat dan membicarakan hal itu?
Why did you say that?
Kenapa bilang begitu?
Why did you guys criticize him like that?
Kenapa kalian mengkritiknya?
You guys are gods. Gods should--
- Kalian dewa. Dewa harus... - Apa setelah aku pergi?
Or was it before that?
Atau sebelum itu?
Were you hoping that I'd leave?
Apa kau berharap aku akan pergi?
You said you're lesser...
Kau bilang kau anak kecil karena menoleransi segalanya.
But...
Tapi kau...
were you crying like a loser?
Apa kau menangis seperti pecundang?
Is that why you opened up to him so quickly?
Itu sebabnya kau cepat menerimanya?
Why are you being like this?
Kenapa kau begini?
Didn't I tell you?
Apa kubilang?
I told you to bear in mind
Kubilang ingatlah
that I can be very jealous of your male friends
aku bisa sangat cemburu pada teman priamu
and that I'm not rational.
dan aku tak rasional.
When did he meet him for the first time?
Kapan dia bertemu dengannya pertama kali?
And what? For the past 1,200 years?
Lalu 1.200 tahun terakhir ini?
Also, the cave. What does that mean?
Juga, gua itu. Apa maksudnya?
Nak-bin is hiding in the Land of the Sky.
Nak-bin bersembunyi di Negeri Langit.
I heard she is in one of the caves that the King owns.
Kudengar di salah satu gua milik Raja.
-Can you ask around? -It won't make any difference.
- Bisa kau cari? - Tak ada bedanya.
No place in the divine realm would be safe for her.
Tak ada tempat di alam suci yang aman baginya.
The same goes for the human world.
Sama seperti di dunia manusia.
I'm not trying to rescue her.
Aku tak ingin menyelamatkannya.
And I'll never forgive her.
Tak akan kumaafkan.
It's just there's something I want to know.
Ada yang ingin kuketahui.
What do you want to know?
Ingin tahu apa?
I want to ask her...
Aku ingin bertanya...
what I was to her.
dia anggap apa aku.
That can't be.
Tidak mungkin.
-Hey, Yeom-mi. -What is it now?
- Hei, Yeom-mi. - Ada apa lagi?
Well...
Ada...
There is someone called A.
Ada seseorang bernama A.
Go on.
Lanjutkan.
Why would A suddenly overreact and get upset during a conversation?
Kenapa A tiba-tiba bereaksi berlebihan dan marah saat berbincang?
I'm sure A is a guy.
Aku yakin A seorang pria.
What?
Apa?
-Yes. -He must have anger management issues.
- Ya. - Dia sulit kendalikan amarah.
Gosh. No, he doesn't.
Astaga. Tidak.
Then he's just a jerk.
Maka dia berengsek.
-No, he isn't. Not at all. -He feels guilty about something.
Tidak sama sekali. Dia merasa bersalah atas sesuatu.
-What? -Guys are like that.
- Apa? - Pria memang begitu.
When they realize that they did something wrong, they get angry.
Saat mereka sadar mereka berbuat salah, mereka marah.
That's how they test women's patience.
Untuk menguji kesabaran wanita.
Break up with him.
Putuskan dia.
-Hello. -Dr. Yun, this is Mr. Min.
- Halo. - Dokter Yun, ini Pak Min.
-Oh, hello. -Have you heard from Mr. Shin at all?
Halo.
No. He's not at work yet?
Tidak. Dia belum di kantor?
I see. All right.
Aku mengerti. Baiklah.
Please call me if you hear anything from him.
Tolong telepon jika kau dihubungi dia.
Okay, I will.
Baik.
MR. SHIN HU-YE
PAK SHIN HU-YE
DR. YUN SO-A
DOKTER YUN SO-A
I've found Biryeom.
Aku menemukan Biryeom.
Tell me.
Katakan.
That day,
Pada hari itu...
you went to that cave, didn't you?
kau ke gua itu, bukan?
Did you...
Apa kau...
meet that guy there?
bertemu dengannya?
Is that...
Apa itu...
when Momyeong died?
saat Momyeong tewas?
Why didn't you tell me?
Kenapa tak katakan?
You said you weren't there.
Katamu kau tak di sana.
You said you wouldn't help me.
Katamu kau tak akan membantuku.
I've thought about it, but I can't help you.
Aku sudah memikirkannya, tapi aku tak bisa membantumu.
I mean, I don't want to.
Maksudku, aku tidak mau.
You broke Mura's heart.
Kau buat Mura patah hati.
You don't deserve to be happy.
Kau tak pantas bahagia.
You need to be punished.
Kau harus dihukum.
Then...
Lalu...
why did you say you didn't go?
kenapa bilang tak pergi?
Right, I shouldn't have gone. I've regretted it thousands of times.
Benar, aku seharusnya tidak pergi. Aku menyesalinya berkali-kali.
"Why did I go there?
"Kenapa aku ke sana?
Why did I even try to do you a favor?
Kenapa aku bahkan mencoba membantumu?
Was helping you more important than Momyeong?"
Kenapa membantumu lebih penting dari Momyeong?"
I keep asking myself.
Aku terus tanyakan itu.
What happened?
Apa yang terjadi?
That guy...
Pria itu...
Why was he there?
Kenapa dia di sana?
He had been imprisoned there.
Dia dikurung di sana.
And she happened to be hiding there.
Dan dia kebetulan sembunyi di sana.
At first, I didn't know he was that kid.
Awalnya, aku tak tahu dia anak itu.
He probably thought I was taking Nak-bin away.
Dia mungkin mengira kubawa Nak-bin pergi.
Right at that moment, the King's servants came to get her.
Tepat pada saat itu, para pelayan Raja datang menjemputnya.
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
Momyeong...
Momyeong.
Momyeong!
Momyeong!
Why...
Kenapa...
Why?
Kenapa?
Why have you kept it from me all this time?
Kenapa kau merahasiakannya selama ini?
It was the King's order.
Itu perintah raja.
The King ordered us not to tell anyone about the boy being there.
Raja memerintahkan kami tak memberi tahu siapa pun tentang anak itu.
As his servants, we had to follow his order.
Sebagai pelayannya, kami harus ikuti perintahnya.
So, Momyeong died...
Momyeong mati...
because of me.
karena aku.
With all due respect, it's no one's fault that Momyeong died.
Dengan segala hormat, bukan salah siapa pun dia tewas.
Momyeong and I share one fate since we're twins.
Momyeong dan aku berbagi takdir karena kami kembar.
One of us was destined to die sooner or later.
Salah satu dari kami ditakdirkan untuk mati, cepat atau lambat.
Yes, it's your fault.
Benar, memang salahmu.
I personally don't think you deserve a slap,
Kupikir kau tak pantas mendapat tamparan,
but Biryeom has been wanting to punch you.
tapi Biryeom ingin memukulmu.
Let's go. You were right.
Ayo. Kau benar.
It does feel nice to slap him.
Rasanya enak menamparnya.
Let it go.
Lepaskan.
I know something is weighing on your mind.
Aku tahu ada yang kau pikirkan.
You resent Habaek...
Kau membenci Habaek...
and find it hard to forgive Mr. Shin.
dan kau sulit memaafkan Pak Shin.
And...
Dan kau...
you hate yourself on top of that. It's all because of this, isn't it?
membenci dirimu sendiri.
-What are you talking about? -You think you ran away.
- Maksudmu? - Kau pikir kau lari.
You think you abandoned Momyeong.
Menurutmu kau menelantarkan Momyeong.
That's why you can't forgive yourself
Itu sebabnya kau tak bisa memaafkan dirimu
and hate everything.
dan benci segalanya.
I'm sorry.
Maaf.
I'm the one who should feel most guilty.
Akulah yang harusnya merasa paling bersalah.
Don't you think so?
Bukankah begitu?
I told you to run away if you ever saw him.
Kusuruh kau kabur jika kau melihatnya.
The God of Fire?
Dewa Api?
He should be our blacksmith.
Dia seharusnya pandai besi kita.
Cut it out.
Hentikan.
If you ever see him, run as fast as you can.
Jika kau melihatnya, lari secepat yang kau bisa.
He'd definitely be stronger than you.
Dia lebih kuat darimu.
Did those words...
Apa kata-kata itu...
get your back up?
mendorongmu?
-No. -You didn't run away.
- Tidak. - Kau tidak melarikan diri.
Jingeon dragged you out of there against your will.
Jingeon menyeretmu, kau tak mau.
You don't know anything.
Kau tak tahu apa-apa.
However...
Namun...
part of you wanted to run away.
sebagian dari dirimu ingin kabur.
Part of you was grateful that Jingeon got you out of there.
Sebagian lagi bersyukur Jingeon mengeluarkanmu.
Is that what you've been thinking?
Begitu menurutmu?
This is why I always say that you're immature.
Karena itu aku selalu bilang kau tidak dewasa.
You didn't abandon Momyeong. You saved Jingeon's life.
Kau tak meninggalkan Momyeong. Kau selamatkan Jingeon.
If something bad happened to you that day,
Jika hal buruk terjadi padamu hari itu, Jingeon tak hidup sekarang.
Do you think the Land of the Sky would've forgiven him?
Apa Negeri Langit bisa memaafkannya?
Don't take my advice from now on.
Jangan terima saranku mulai sekarang.
There are always unintended consequences like this.
Selalu ada risiko seperti ini.
And...
Juga...
just think of this...
anggap ini penghiburan terhebat...
as the greatest consolation I can give you.
yang bisa kuberikan.
-Feel better now? -Are you kidding me?
- Merasa enakan? - Kau bercanda?
He had been imprisoned there.
Dia dikurung di sana.
And she happened to be hiding there.
Dan dia kebetulan sembunyi di sana.
Mr. Shin.
Pak Shin.
I know that you're here.
Aku tahu kau di sini.
I can feel that you're here.
Aku merasakan kau di sini.
Are we playing hide-and-seek now?
Apa kita bermain petak umpat?
I fell.
Aku jatuh.
Is he not here?
Dia tak ada di sini?
That's odd.
Aneh.
Damn it!
Sial!
He's not like us.
Dia tak seperti kami.
He's not one of them?
Dia bukan mereka?
Then what is he?
Lalu dia itu apa?
He's from the world of gods, but he's not a god?
Dia berasal dari dunia dewa, tapi bukan dewa?
I don't know who my mother is.
Aku tak mengenal ibuku.
My father...
Ayahku...
treated me like a monster.
memperlakukanku seperti monster.
I wasn't supposed to be born.
Aku tak seharusnya dilahirkan.
Disgrace.
Aib.
That was my name.
Itu namaku dulu.
My father was afraid people would find out about me,
Ayahku takut orang-orang akan tahu tentangku...
so he chose to imprison me for a long time.
jadi dia mengurungku lama.
The notion of family is different in the divine realm.
Konsep keluarga berbeda di alam suci.
He said the notion of family is different in the world of gods.
Katanya konsep keluarga berbeda di dunia dewa.
Could it be...
Mungkinkah...
No way.
Tidak mungkin.
What am I going to do...
Aku harus bagaimana...
when I see him?
saat bertemu dengannya?
Are you going somewhere?
Kau mau pergi?
No.
Tidak.
I'm sorry about last night.
Maaf soal semalam.
Did something happen?
Apa terjadi sesuatu?
No.
Tidak.
-Well... -Yes?
- Itu... - Ya.
Never mind.
Lupakan saja.
Where were you all day?
Di mana kau seharian?
Did you meet your friends and try to borrow money from them?
Kau bertemu temanmu dan meminjam uang dari mereka?
The reality must've hit you.
Kenyataan pasti sulit bagimu.
Food.
Makanan.
You still remember it.
Kau masih ingat.
Let's eat something. How about curry?
Ayo makan. Mau kari?
-What is that? -You'll see. It's yellow.
- Apa itu? - Kau akan tahu. Berwarna kuning.
I'll go pick up some curry paste.
Aku akan beli pasta kari.
Peel some potatoes, please.
Tolong kupas kentangnya.
Do a good job, okay?
Kerja yang bagus, ya?
How to peel potatoes.
Cara mengupas kentang.
HOW TO PEEL POTATOES
CARA MENGUPAS KENTANG
Hello?
Halo?
The potatoes are sprouting.
Kentangnya bertunas.
The sprouts are playing rock-paper-scissors.
Tunasnya bermain hompimpa.
What?
Apa?
All right.
Baiklah.
Is he addicted to surfing the internet?
Dia kecanduan Internet?
JAHA MART
TOKO JAHA
Do you have potatoes?
Ada kentang?
How ugly.
Jelek sekali.
HOW TO MAKE CURRY
CARA MEMBUAT KARI
Curry...
Kari...
And...
Dan...
I bought the curry paste...
Aku beli pasta kari...
and potatoes.
dan kentang.
The curry paste is here. Potatoes and...
Ada pasta kari. Kentang dan...
And bell peppers.
Paprika.
HOW TO MAKE CURRY
CARA MEMBUAT KARI
Hold on! Calm down.
Tunggu! Tenanglah.
It's me. You don't recognize me?
Ini aku. Kau tak mengenaliku?
It's you.
Kau.
Yes, I'm the voracious deity, Jugeollin.
Ya, aku dewa rakus, Jugeollin.
Hold on.
Tunggu.
Hear me out.
Dengarkan aku.
Hear me out first.
Dengarkan dulu.
I want you to see Hu-ye.
Aku ingin kau bertemu Hu-ye.
Please.
Kumohon.
Mr. Shin.
Pak Shin.
-Just a moment. -Let go.
- Tunggu. - Lepas.
-Look at me. -Let go of me!
- Lihat aku. - Lepaskan aku!
Stay still.
Jangan bergerak.
It's okay.
Tak apa-apa.
It's all right.
Tidak apa-apa.
Stay still.
Jangan bergerak.
It's okay.
Tak apa-apa.
-Yun-- -Yes, it's me.
- Yun... - Ya, ini aku.
Where are you?
Di mana kau?
-Are you okay? -Yes, I'm fine.
- Kau baik-baik saja? - Ya, aku baik.
Don't worry.
Jangan cemas.
Is it that prick?
Apa Si Bedebah itu? Kau bersamanya?
Come home now.
Cepatlah pulang.
I'm totally fine.
Aku baik-baik saja.
I'll see you later.
Sampai nanti.
Come home now.
Pulanglah sekarang.
You don't even know him.
Kau bahkan tak kenal dia.
He's not the kind of person you think he is.
Dia tak seperti yang kau pikirkan.
I know him well enough.
Aku cukup mengenalnya.
-What? -So don't worry.
- Apa? - Jangan khawatir.
He won't harm me.
Dia tak akan menyakitiku.
I'll be home soon. Don't worry.
Aku segera pulang. Tenanglah.
See?
Lihat?
She's okay, right?
Dia baik, 'kan?
You thought he'd harm her? Mr. Shin might be a dangerous man,
Pikirmu dia akan melukainya? Pak Shin mungkin berbahaya,
but he'd never harm that girl.
tapi dia tak akan menyakiti gadis itu.
-She must be at the farm. -Just let him have her.
- Dia di peternakan. - Serahkan padanya.
-That'll be better for her too. -Help me get there.
Itu lebih baik untuknya.
There is nothing you can do for her.
Tak ada yang bisa kau lakukan untuknya.
Mr. Shin is very rich.
Tuan Shin sangat kaya.
It'll take too long by car.
Terlalu lama jika naik mobil.
-Help me, please. -I don't want to.
- Tolong aku. - Aku tak mau.
Mr. Shin.
Pak Shin.
Leave.
Pergi.
-Mr. Shin. -Please!
- Pak Shin. - Kumohon!
Leave, please.
Kumohon, pergilah.
Don't come near me.
Jangan mendekatiku.
I destroy everything.
Aku hancurkan segalanya.
If you stay with me...
Jika kau bersamaku...
you'll be unhappy.
kau tak akan bahagia.
I almost...
Aku hampir...
killed you once.
membunuhmu sekali.
Some things never change.
Ada hal yang tak bisa berubah.
Even if you change its appearance,
Bahkan jika penampilannya berubah...
it just never changes.
itu tak pernah berubah.
No matter how hard you try,
Betapa kerasnya usahamu...
you keep going back.
kau terus kembali.
You go back...
Kau kembali...
again and again.
lagi dan lagi.
So...
Jadi, dari mana kau mulai?
Are you trying to say...
Apa maksudmu...
that your sins will never disappear?
dosamu tak akan pernah hilang?
That's right.
Benar.
I am capable of...
Aku bisa melakukan...
committing another sin anytime.
dosa lain kapan saja.
-I'll never change. -You're wrong.
- Aku tak akan pernah berubah. - Kau salah.
You're not that kind of person.
Kau bukan orang seperti itu.
"Person"?
Orang?
Then would you rather be a god?
Apa kau lebih suka menjadi dewa?
What would you rather be? A god or a human being?
Apa maumu? Dewa atau manusia?
Be a human being.
Jadilah manusia.
That's better.
Itu lebih baik.
A human being...
Manusia...
suits you better.
lebih cocok untukmu.
You've helped so many people. You've supported so many children.
Kau membantu banyak orang. Kau mendukung banyak anak.
You've helped countless ill people get better.
Kau membantu banyak orang sakit jadi lebih baik.
You've saved so many lives.
Kau menyelamatkan banyak nyawa.
Do you know what you are to those people?
Kau tahu siapa dirimu bagi mereka?
You're like a god to them.
Kau bagai dewa bagi mereka.
The work you've done as a human being...
Tindakan yang kau lakukan sebagai manusia
was the work of a god.
adalah pekerjaan dewa.
Let's say God is looking down from above.
Katakanlah Tuhan melihat ke bawah dari atas.
He'd see a tiny human being helping other humans
Dia akan melihat manusia yang kecil
in a tiny country, on this tiny planet called Earth.
di negara kecil, di planet kecil bernama bumi ini.
God would say, "I'm so busy.
Tuhan akan berkata, "Aku sangat sibuk.
Thank you for helping me out.
Terima kasih sudah membantuku.
Well done.
Bagus.
My blessing upon you."
Semoga kau diberkati."
I once told you...
Aku pernah bilang...
that all the trees you planted will become a big forest one day.
semua pohon yang kau tanam
The life you've been living...
Hidup yang kau jalani...
will never disappear.
tak akan pernah hilang.
If you choose to be a human being,
Jika kau memilih menjadi manusia...
I will be...
aku...
on your side.
akan mendukungmu.
No matter...
Apa pun...
what happens,
yang terjadi, aku akan selalu di sisimu.
I'll be...
Aku akan...
your god.
jadi dewamu.
But I'm...
Tapi aku...
So-a.
So-a.
Let's go.
Ayo.
I'm his psychiatrist.
Aku psikiaternya.
Is this jealousy?
Apakah ini cemburu?
I suppose this is better than having no jealousy at all.
Ini lebih baik daripada tak cemburu sama sekali.
But I've never been with a guy who's the jealous type,
Tapi aku tak pernah bersama pria pencemburu,
so I can't really tell if this is jealousy or not.
jadi, aku tak tahu apakah ini cemburu atau bukan.
You haven't eaten anything?
Kau belum makan apa pun?
I can tell you're hungry.
Aku tahu kau lapar.
It's too late for curry.
Sudah telat untuk kari.
I'm sorry, but we'll just have to have some cup noodles.
Maaf, kita makan mi instan saja.
Wait.
Tunggu.
-What was that about? -Let's stop there.
- Apa itu tadi? - Cukup sudah.
-What? -I said, no more.
- Apa? - Kubilang cukup.
But why?
Tapi kenapa?
"Why?"
Kenapa?
Never mind.
Lupakan saja.
-Shall we continue? -No.
- Bisa kita lanjutkan? - Tidak.
Candy...
Permen tak boleh dimakan sekaligus.
-Sorry? -I'll see you tomorrow.
- Apa? - Sampai jumpa besok.
What did he just say?
Dia bilang apa?
What's this about? Is he trying to train me or what?
Ada apa ini? Apa dia mencoba melatihku?
He's acting like a total womanizer.
Sikapnya seperti mata keranjang.
All right. 10,001, 10,002, 10,003...
Baik, 10.001, 10.002, 10.003...
-Lord Habaek. -Keep going.
- Tuan Habaek. - Teruskan.
Okay. 10,009, 10,010.
Baiklah, 10.009, 10.010.
My Lord, why are you being like this?
Tuan, kenapa kau seperti ini?
This fruit juice quenches thirst like nothing else does.
Jus buah ini memuaskan rasa haus seperti biasa.
That totally hydrated me.
Ini sangat menyegarkan.
-What was that about? -Let's stop there.
- Apa itu tadi? - Cukup sudah.
-What? -I said, no more.
- Apa? - Kubilang cukup.
But why?
Tapi kenapa?
Gosh, why on earth did I say that?
Ya ampun. Kenapa aku mengatakan itu?
-What's up? -What?
- Ada apa? - Apa?
Nothing. Don't mind me.
Jangan pedulikan aku.
Why are you all wet?
Kenapa kau basah kuyup?
I'm sweating. It's such a nuisance. I need to use the place called "bathroom."
Aku berkeringat. Mengesalkan.
What did you say?
Apa katamu?
Why do you need to use my bathroom?
Kenapa ke kamar mandiku?
You have that rubber bin.
Kau punya tong itu.
You told me not to sit in it all the time.
Kau melarangku duduk setiap saat.
What? Oh, right.
Apa? Benar.
Well, what I meant was...
Yang kumaksud adalah...
Where is it? Upstairs?
Di mana itu? Di atas?
-What's wrong? -Nothing.
- Ada apa? - Tak ada.
I have to go to work.
Aku harus pergi bekerja.
Really? Then let's come home together later.
Sungguh? Kalau begitu, ayo pulang bersama.
What?
Apa?
Okay, sure.
Tentu.
Gosh, I must be losing my mind.
Astaga, aku pasti sudah gila.
That man...
Pria itu…
What the heck did he do to me last night?
Apa yang dia lakukan padaku semalam?
MR. SHIN HU-YE
PAK SHIN HU-YE
Can we meet briefly?
Bisakah kita bertemu sebentar?
You should see how your patient is doing after our session, Doctor.
Kau harus lihat keadaan pasien setelah sesi, Dokter.
PROPOSAL
PROPOSAL
CEO SHIN HU-YE
CEO SHIN HU-YE
Can you go to Songdo?
Bisa pergi ke Songdo?
They're saying they need me there, but I think you can take care of it.
Katanya mereka butuh aku, tapi kau bisa mengurusnya.
-Mr. Kim will fill you in. -Sure.
- Pak Kim akan menjelaskan. - Baik.
-What brings you here? -What?
- Kenapa kau kemari? - Apa?
If it's about Block World, I have nothing more to tell you.
Kalau soal Block World, tak ada yang bisa kukatakan.
You should let your grandfather know.
Kau harus beri tahu kakekmu.
Okay.
Baik.
But that's not why I'm here. I was just wondering...
Bukan itu tujuanku. Aku ingin tahu...
Are you busy?
Kau sibuk?
Do you need to talk to Mr. Min?
Kau perlu bicara dengan Pak Min?
Yes.
Ya.
You know I called you so many times, right?
Kau tahu aku menelepon berkali-kali.
-I didn't want to talk to you. -Why not?
- Aku tak mau bicara denganmu. - Kenapa?
Tell me, Mr. Min.
Katakan, Pak Min.
-Am I supposed to talk like a counselor? -What? Yes.
- Apa aku harus bicara seperti konselor? - Apa? Ya.
Are you the one who told Dr. Yun to vacate the office space?
Kau yang mengusir Dokter Yun?
What?
Apa?
Yes. How did you know?
Ya. Bagaimana kau tahu?
That's not why I gave you the information.
Bukan itu tujuanku.
How dare you misuse the information? You're shameless.
Beraninya kau salah gunakan info? Tak tahu malu.
"Shameless"?
Tak tahu malu?
Is that why you're mad at me?
Itu sebabnya kau marah kepadaku?
Do you like her too? Is that it?
Kau suka dia juga? Begitu?
I don't like anyone.
Aku tak suka siapa pun.
I just want you to become a decent human being.
Aku hanya ingin kau jadi manusia yang baik.
"A decent human being"?
Manusia baik?
Don't contact me until you think you've become a decent human being.
Jangan hubungi aku sampai kau pikir kau manusia yang baik.
No more counseling for you.
Tak ada lagi saran untukmu.
I'm busy. I have to go.
Aku pergi.
And your plan has failed.
Rencanamu gagal.
Become a decent human being?
Jadi manusia yang baik?
That jerk!
Dasar bedebah.
The flowers we planted have already grown this much?
Bunga yang kita tanam sudah tumbuh?
I've been watering them every day.
Kusiram setiap hari.
Butterflies also came by and gave them love.
Kupu-kupu juga datang dan memberi mereka cinta.
That's why the flowers could bloom like this.
Berkat itu bunga-bunga bisa mekar.
Min, you're so smart.
Min, kau sangat pintar.
Don't grow up too fast.
Jangan tumbuh terlalu cepat. Aku akan bosan.
-I see that you have a guest. -Hello.
- Sepertinya kau punya tamu. - Halo.
Hi.
Hai.
Min, say hi. She's a doctor.
Min, ucapkan salam. Dia seorang dokter.
Hello.
Halo.
Yes, hi. You have such a pretty name.
Hai. Kau punya nama yang cantik.
Mr. Shin, why is a doctor here?
Pak Shin, kenapa ada dokter di sini?
I'm not sick.
Aku tidak sakit.
-She's here to see me. -Really?
- Dia ingin bertemu denganku. - Sungguh?
Is she Ms. Yun by any chance?
Apa mungkin dia Nona Yun?
I heard you telling someone on the phone that you'll keep your promise
Kudengar kau memberi tahu orang di telepon kau akan menepati janjimu
and saying, "Yes, Ms. Yun."
dan berkata, "Ya, Nona Yun."
I could tell that you were in a really good mood that day.
Aku tahu suasana hatimu baik saat itu.
-Mr. Shin, you must-- -Min.
Pak Shin, kau harus...
Oh, is it a secret?
Apa itu rahasia?
No, it's not that.
Bukan begitu.
Min should leave now.
Min harus pergi.
She's my neighbor
Dia tetanggaku
and my only friend.
dan satu-satunya temanku.
Her parents passed away, so she lives with her grandmother.
Orang tuanya meninggal, dia tinggal bersama neneknya.
Her grandmother has to see her doctor twice a month.
Neneknya harus periksa dua kali sebulan.
She always comes with her to get some fresh air and so on.
Dia selalu datang dengannya untuk mencari udara segar.
She can draw very well.
Dia pintar menggambar.
I guess she can see everything with her heart.
Kurasa dia bisa melihat semua dengan hatinya.
Her eyes...
Matanya…
It was my doing.
Itu perbuatanku.
For a few years after coming here,
Beberapa tahun setelah kemari,
I didn't know how to control my powers.
aku tak bisa mengendalikan kekuatanku.
Regardless of my intentions,
Terlepas dari niatku,
I had no way of knowing when and what could happen,
aku tak tahu kapan dan apa yang bisa terjadi,
so I was always anxious.
aku selalu cemas.
On my first day at the farm,
Pada hari pertamaku di peternakan,
I saw Min wrapped in a blanket.
aku melihat Min terbungkus selimut.
When her grandmother stepped out for a brief moment,
Saat neneknya keluar sejenak,
a wild dog attacked her.
seekor anjing liar menyerangnya.
I wanted to get the dog off of her,
Aku ingin mengusir anjing itu.
so I used my power.
Kupakai kekuatanku.
The dog died,
Anjing itu mati...
and the baby...
dan bayinya...
She lost her eyesight.
Dia kehilangan penglihatan.
I think of Min's life...
Aku menganggap hidup Min...
as my own.
seperti hidupku.
Ms. Yun.
Nona Yun.
-I just made up my mind about something. -Sorry?
Aku baru memutuskan sesuatu.
"It won't be a bad idea to just enjoy this regardless of this woman's intentions."
"Bukan ide buruk untuk menikmati ini tanpa menghiraukan niat wanita ini."
What do you mean?
Apa maksudmu?
Well, you don't need to know the specifics.
Kau tak perlu tahu secara spesifik.
Ms. Yun.
Nona Yun.
Did we perhaps...
Apa kita pernah bertemu di masa lalu?
Pardon?
Apa?
Well, it just feels like...
Sepertinya kita...
we've crossed paths...
pernah bertemu...
a long time ago.
sudah sangat lama.
It's okay.
Tak apa-apa.
It's all right.
Tidak apa-apa.
Stay still.
Jangan bergerak.
It's okay.
Tak apa-apa.
Sir.
Pak.
-We're ready for the meeting. -Okay.
Rapat akan mulai.
I should go. I'll see you later.
Aku harus pergi. Sampai nanti.
Okay.
Baiklah. Apa?
"Later"?
Nanti?
Why is she sleeping when she called me over?
Kenapa dia tidur saat dia memanggilku?
Why are you here again?
Kenapa kau kemari lagi?
What? Me?
Apa? Aku?
Yes, you.
Ya, kau.
I'm here for my shift. You told me to just sit here.
Ini sif kerjaku. Kau menyuruhku hanya duduk di sini.
What?
Apa?
What did you say?
Apa katamu?
What? Speak louder.
Apa? Bicara lebih keras.
He is...
Dia...
Yes, go on.
Ya, lanjutkan.
-Who are you talking about? -He is...
- Siapa yang kau bicarakan? - Dia...
He's the one who saved me.
Dia yang menyelamatkanku.
It was him.
Itu dia.
But...
Tapi...
What?
Apa?
What are you talking about now?
Apa katamu?
I can't hear you!
Aku tak bisa mendengarmu!
-When did you get here? -A few minutes ago.
- Kapan kau tiba? - Beberapa menit lalu.
What kind of dream made you that aggressive?
Mimpi apa kau sampai agresif?
Gosh, my goodness!
Astaga.
I saw your landlady in my dream.
Aku melihat tuanmu di mimpiku.
Why does she have to brag about her boyfriend even in my dream?
Kenapa dia harus menyombongkan kekasihnya bahkan di mimpiku?
-What? -I can't believe this.
- Apa? - Aku tak percaya ini.
She's making me feel upset about the fact that I'm single.
Dia mengejekku karena aku jomlo.
I was even going to do a reading for her, thinking it might be a bad omen.
Aku bahkan akan meramalnya, kukira itu pertanda buruk.
I can't believe she was bragging about some man saving her life.
Aku tak percaya dia menyombongkan diri soal pria yang menyelamatkan hidupnya.
But you must really be helping me boost my psychic powers.
Tapi kau pasti membantuku meningkatkan kekuatan batinku.
I can hear things again.
Aku bisa mendengar lagi.
Oh, right. The new owner of the building will stop by later today.
Pemilik gedung baru akan mampir nanti.
Really? It's so messy here, though.
Sungguh? Di sini sangat berantakan.
-Do we have anything to give him? -I'll go buy some cold drinks.
- Apa kita beri hadiah? - Aku beli minuman.
Hey, Hyeong-sik.
Hai, Hyeong-sik.
Why are you crying?
Kenapa kau menangis?
What? Your appendix burst?
Apa? Usus buntumu meledak?
Yes, okay. I'll leave right now.
Ya, baiklah. Aku segera pergi.
Which hospital are you at?
Kau di rumah sakit apa?
Hey.
Hai.
Hey!
Hai!
Jeez, that slacker.
Astaga, si pemalas itu.
Why make such a fuss about appendicitis? My goodness.
Kenapa ribut soal usus buntu? Astaga.
He's useless.
Dia tak berguna.
Is this the only rag we have?
Apa hanya ini kain kami?
I wonder if he's on his way here.
Apa dia sedang kemari?
I should ask him if he can bring some rags.
Aku akan minta dia bawakan kain.
What's wrong with me?
Ada apa denganku?
WATER DEMON
IBLIS AIR
MY SERVANT
PELAYANKU
What happened to your face?
Kenapa mukamu?
I just did it for fun.
Aku hanya bercanda.
What?
Apa?
No, it's nothing.
Bukan apa-apa.
Do you find me attractive?
Apa aku menarik?
Well...
Itu...
Can you bring a few rags when you're coming?
Apa kau bisa bawakan beberapa kain saat kemari?
Am I attractive or not?
Aku menarik atau tidak?
-My gosh, I have to go! -Hey, what's wrong?
- Astaga, aku harus pergi! - Ada apa?
Gosh, what did this guy...
Astaga, apa yang dilakukan...
do to me last night?
pria ini padaku semalam?
I must be possessed by some dirty-minded evil spirit.
Aku pasti dirasuki roh jahat yang nakal.
Why does she keep losing her mind?
Kenapa dia terus menjadi gila?
How dare she order me to bring rags...
Beraninya dia menyuruhku membawa kain...
Hey.
Hai.
How did you get in here?
Kok bisa kau masuk?
Don't you think that question is a little weird?
Bukankah pertanyaan ini agak aneh?
I can go anywhere. I'm a god.
Aku bisa ke mana saja. Aku dewa.
I didn't want to see you either.
Aku juga tak mau melihatmu.
I came because Mura kept insisting that I should.
Ini karena Mura bersikeras.
She told me to hear what you have to say.
Jadi, aku ingin mendengar pendapatmu.
-How's Jingeon? -He's fine.
- Bagaimana Jingeon? - Dia baik.
No matter what he says,
Apa pun yang dia katakan...
it is my fault that Momyeong died.
Momyeong tewas karena aku.
I caused his death.
Aku penyebab kematiannya.
But I've been living...
Tapi aku hidup...
without knowing that he died because of me.
tanpa tahu bahwa dia mati karena aku.
That's why you're so angry.
Itu sebabnya kau murka.
I'm sorry.
Maaf.
This is what Mura wanted you...
Ini yang Mura ingin...
to hear from me, right?
kau dengar dariku?
He was probably...
Dia mungkin...
trying to protect Nak-bin.
mencoba melindungi Nak-bin.
It must've been his first time seeing a female human after many years.
Itu pasti pertama kali dia melihat wanita setelah bertahun-tahun.
I can't think that far yet. I need some time.
Aku belum bisa berpikir sejauh itu. Aku butuh waktu.
Wait.
Tunggu.
Didn't he ask you for money with this kind of face?
Dia minta uang dengan wajah seperti ini?
-He did. -He did?
- Benar. - Benarkah?
-So? -I told him that no one
- Lalu? - Kubilang tak ada yang
carries around cash these days.
bawa uang tunai sekarang.
-And? -"Then give me your credit card.
- Lalu? - "Berikan kartu kreditmu.
If you don't have one, give me some diamonds.
Jika tak punya, beri aku berlian.
When I refused, he said, "This is the King's order."
Saat aku menolak, dia bilang, "Ini perintah Raja."
I'm speechless. Make sure you never give him any money.
Aku tak bisa berkata-kata. Jangan beri dia uang.
Why don't you stop doing favors for him?
Kenapa kau tak berhenti membantunya?
You said you weren't going to take him to the farm, but you did.
Katamu tak akan bawa dia ke peternakan, ternyata kau ajak.
No more favors for him.
Tak ada bantuan lagi.
I'll hang him out to dry so that he goes back as soon as possible.
Akan kupersulit dia agar kembali secepatnya.
What?
Apa?
Can I kiss you?
Boleh kucium?
-Must I freeze your tongue? -Just one kiss.
- Mau kubekukan lidahmu? - Sekali.
Start driving.
Mulai menyetir.
All right. Do you want to take it to the next level when we get home?
Baik. Apa kau ingin lebih jauh saat kita pulang?
Should I tell him not to come?
Haruskah kularang dia datang?
I'll tell him not to come today.
Akan kularang dia datang.
We can go home together starting tomorrow. My gosh!
Bisa pulang bersama mulai besok. Astaga.
NURSE YU
PERAWAT YU
Hyeong-sik is fine.
Hyeong-sik baik-baik saja.
HYEONG-SIK IS FINE
HYEONG-SIK BAIK-BAIK SAJA
As for picking up drinks for the new landlord...
Mengenai minuman untuk pemilik baru...
Jeez, that slacker!
Dasar pemalas.
Gosh, I'm getting a headache.
Kepalaku jadi sakit.
What? "Bring some rags"?
Apa? Bawalah kain?
Who does she think I am?
Dia pikir aku siapa?
-What are you doing here? -Hello, how have you been?
- Sedang apa kau di sini? - Apa kabar?
That's none of your business.
Bukan urusanmu.
Why are you here?
Kenapa kau di sini?
-I came to say hello as the new landlord. -"Landlord"?
Aku menyapa sebagai pemilik baru.
What's that?
Apa itu?
You don't need to know. They say landlords are above God.
Tak perlu tahu.
Landlords can be quite powerful at times.
Pemilik bisa sangat kuat.
I don't give a shit. Just get lost.
Aku tak peduli. Enyahlah.
I've already said this to Ms. Yun,
Aku sudah katakan ini pada Nona Yun,
but I'll say it again.
tapi akan kukatakan lagi.
You see, what I'm best at
Begini, keahlianku adalah
-is waiting. -What?
- menunggu. - Apa?
No one can defy time and gravity.
Tak ada yang bisa melawan waktu dan gravitasi.
You have to return to the divine realm eventually,
Kau harus kembali ke alam suci,
but I'll still be living here with her.
tapi aku akan tetap di sini bersamanya.
So?
Lalu?
I'll do all the things that you'll never be able
Aku akan melakukan semua hal yang tak bisa kau lakukan dengannya.
Thankfully,
Syukurlah, banyak yang bisa kuberikan.
What did you say?
Apa katamu?
Excuse me, guys.
Permisi.
What brings you here? You don't have an appointment today.
Kenapa kau kemari? Kita tak ada janji hari ini.
-I thought you knew that I was coming. -What?
Kukira kau tahu aku akan datang.
You didn't mention anything when I saw you earlier.
Kau tak menyebut apa pun saat kita bertemu.
Don't say anything.
Jangan katakan apa pun.
Don't talk to him.
Jangan bicara dengannya.
Lock the door and leave the key under the flower pot.
Kunci pintunya dan tinggalkan kunci di bawah pot.
Calm down, will you? I'm worried we might get into an accident.
Tenang. Aku cemas kita akan kecelakaan.
Is this also jealousy?
Ini juga cemburu?
This does feel more like jealousy than what you did yesterday.
Ini lebih terasa cemburu daripada yang kemarin.
Anyway, you're charming even when you're jealous.
Kau menarik bahkan saat kau cemburu.
You're charming even when you're angry.
Kau menarik bahkan saat kau marah.
-Where are we going? -I don't know.
- Kita ke mana? - Entahlah.
Do you want to go see the sunset?
Mau melihat matahari terbenam?
Let's hurry. Who knows when someone else will show up and bother us?
Ayo cepat. Entah siapa lagi yang akan mengganggu kita.
Come on. Let's go.
Ayolah.
Over there. The sun will set in that direction.
Di sana.
Let's watch from here.
Ayo lihat dari sini.
This is such a memorable image. It's the perfect way to end the day.
Ini mengesankan. Cara sempurna mengakhiri hari.
I guess this is why people purposely go see the sunset even when they're busy.
Kurasa ini alasan orang melihatnya bahkan saat mereka sibuk.
To tell you the truth,
Sejujurnya...
I came here once with my parents when I was young.
aku pernah kemari bersama orang tuaku saat masih kecil.
Back then, I didn't get this kind of feeling.
Saat itu, aku tak merasakan hal seperti ini.
My dad kept worrying...
Ayah terus mengkhawatirkan
about the kids we left at home,
anak-anak yang kami tinggalkan di rumah
and my mom was mad at him for being like that.
dan ibuku marah kepadanya karena begitu.
They kept arguing nonstop, and I was on pins and needles.
Mereka terus berdebat dan aku gelisah.
So we just had a bowl of clam noodles and went home.
Jadi, kami makan mie kerang dan pulang.
What are you thinking?
Apa yang kau pikirkan?
Tomorrow,
Besok...
the day after tomorrow,
lusa...
and the day after that.
dan keesokan harinya.
Your future without me.
Masa depanmu tanpa aku.
Let's only think about today.
Kita pikirkan saja hari ini.
You said something very impressive a little while ago.
Kau pernah mengatakan hal yang mengesankan.
You told me about those who believe
Tentang mereka yang percaya
they can live the rest of their lives with their memories of today.
bisa menjalani sisa hidup mereka dengan kenangan hari ini.
I said that?
Aku bilang itu?
When?
Kapan?
A while ago.
Belum lama.
When something fades in the sun, it becomes history.
Saat sesuatu memudar di bawah sinar mentari, itu jadi sejarah.
And when something soaks up the moonlight,
Dan saat sesuatu menyerap sinar bulan,
it becomes a myth.
itu menjadi mitos.
That means our story...
Berarti kisah kita...
will become a myth.
akan jadi mitos.
-I've received the message. -Please get ready, Lord Habaek.
- Aku terima pesannya. - Bersiaplah, Tuan Habaek.
Can I be greedy?
Bolehkah aku serakah?
Let me say this just in case. You know what will happen if you don't return?
Biar aku katakan ini.
-Let's stay together. -All right.
- Mari tetap bersama. - Ya.
Habaek will perish if he doesn't ascend the throne.
Habaek binasa jika tak naik takhta.
I don't want that kind of tragedy.
Aku tak mau tragedi terjadi.
Try your best not to be lonely for as long as you can.
Usahakan jangan kesepian selama mungkin.
Can you live without him?
Kau bisa hidup tanpanya?
Then let me tell you something you don't know.
Kuberi tahu sesuatu yang tak kau ketahui.
He's the one who saved me.
Dialah yang menyelamatkanku.
-It means you're going to die. -But the person who saved me...
Artinya kau akan mati.